Guide to the Charles Abrams papers, 1923-1970.
Abrams, Charles papers, 1923-1970
- Series V. Articles and Speeches
  - "Report to the Councils." Citizens Councils of SCAD, 1957-05-10 (Box 120)
  - "SCAD's Housing Jurisdiction." Long Island Conference on Housing, Rockville Center., 1957-05-26 (Box 120)
  - Harvard Urban Design Conference, 1957-05 (Box 120)
    Speech, reported in Architectural Record (May)
  - "United States Housing: A New Program" Special Supplement, The New Leader, 1958-01-13 (Box 120)
    Reprinted in Congressional Record Appendix, 104, no. 6 'January 15: 284-^6. Publis
  - Golden Agers' Hobby Fair, Buffalo Mayor's Committee on Recreation for the Aging and the Western New York Geriatrics Society, 1958-05-05 (Box 120)
    >Buffalo
  - "Regional Planning Legislation in Under-Developed Areas." United Nations Housing Seminar, 1958-07-27 (Box 120)
    >Tokyo
  - New jersey Welfare Council, 1958-10-28 (Box 120)
    Speech, published as "Poverty amidst Plenty." Interracial Review
    >Atlantic City
  - "Lets Find Out." WCBS., 1958-11-23 (Box 120)
  - National Association of Intergroup Relations Officials, Pittsburgh, 1958-11 (Box 120)
  - "Determination on Reconsideration." American Jewish Congress v. Arabian American Oil Company before SCAD. Case no. C-4296-56, 1959-01-26 (Box 120)
  - Review of Pilot Project, India, by Albert Mayer, et aL The New Leader., 1959-04-15 (Box 120)
  - WMCA, 1959-04-15 (Box 120)
  - "Credit Terms in Relation to Demand for Housing." Subcommittee on Housing, Committee on Banking and Currency, U. S. Senate., 1959-05-14 (Box 120)
  - "Are We Nearing the End of Public Housing?" Viewpoint, WRCA., 1958-1959 (Box 120)
  - "Population Explosion and the Housing Problem." Unsolved Problems in a Changing World, New School for Social Research, 1960-01-11 (Box 120)
  - Review of Property Values and Race: Studies in Seven Cities, by Luigi Laurenti. Submitted to The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science., 1960-04-06 (Box 120)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, Subcommittee on Housing, Committee on Banking and Currency, U. S. Senate, 1960-05-23 (Box 120)
    Testimony. See May 14,1959
  - "Housing the Nation's Low- and Middle-Income Families." Governor's Conference on Housing, 1960-06-13 (Box 120)
    >Los Angeles
  - Speech, 1960-07-13 (Box 120)
    Upon arrival in Ireland
  - "Urban Renewal." Irish Branch, Town Planning Institute, 1960-08-02 (Box 120)
    >Dublin
  - Memorandum on "Roor Loan Schema", 1960-11-14 (Box 120)
    >Ghana
  - Focal Point Conference, 1961-10-02 (Box 120)
    Speech, pictures
  - Cooper Square Community Development Committee, 1961-10-24 (Box 120)
  - Comments on Paul Ylvisaker's speech. New School for Social Research., 1961-10-06 (Box 120)
    The speech itself was not filmed
  - "The Legal Basis for Reorganizing Metropolitan Areas in a Free Society Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, 1961-06-29 (Box 120)
  - "Housing and Urban Development Activities in the United States.", 1962-03-12 (Box 120)
    Possibly for UN conference
  - Speech, 1962-04-09 (Box 120)
    On the Housing Executive Order
  - Governor's Conference on California Growth, 1962-06-22 (Box 120)
  - UN Housing Conference, 1962-02-07-1962-02-21 (Box 120)
    Speech. See also, March 12 and May 15
  - "Cities of the World." The Eduard C. Lindeman Lectures, The New School Associates., 1963-03-26 (Box 120)
  - 1963-04-22 (Box 120)
    Statement
  - "The Ethics of Power in a Welfare Society." Equal Opportunity in Housing: A National Conference, National Committee Against Discrimination In Housing, 1963-04-25 (Box 120)
  - "The Low-Income Housing Crisis." Massachusetts Committee on Discrimination in Housing, 1963-11-22 (Box 120)
    >Boston
  - "The Negro Issue and Housing." University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee, 1964-03-18 (Box 120)
  - "Economic Aspects of Public Housing." Massachusetts Committee on Discrimination in Housing, 1964-05-15 (Box 120)
  - "Deten lining Priorities for New York City." The Future by Design Symposium, Panel III, 115-152, City Planning Commission., 1964-10-16 (Box 120)
  - Memorial of Catherine Bauer Wurster, New York Metropolian Chapter, National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials., 1964-12-10 (Box 120)
  - "Preface." Downtown U.S.A., by Oscar H. Steiner. Dobbs Ferry: Oceana Publications., 1964 (Box 120)
  - Fair Housing Conference, National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing., 1965-06-29 (Box 120)
  - "The Uses of Land in Cities." Scientific American, 213, No. 3, 1965-09 (Box 120)
    Reprinted by Knopf
  - AID-HHFA Conference, 1965-10-08 (Box 120)
    Columbia University
  - "The Rise of New Towns." America's Crisis Series. National Educational Television script, 28-36, 1966-03-14 (Box 120)
  - "Opportunities in Taxation for Achieving Planning Purposes." American Society of Planning Officials, 1966-06-05 (Box 120)
    See Real Estate Section, New York Times, June 5
  - "Planning to Preserve the Central City and Prevent Urban Sprawl." American Press Institute, 1966-05-16 (Box 120)
  - "The Role of the University in the Urban Environment." Alumni Seminar. Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1967-09-10 (Box 120)
    See Columbia Daily Spectator, April 6,1968
  - "Housing in the Year 2000." The Next Fifty Years Conference, American Institute of Planners, 1967-10-05 (Box 120)
    Published in Environment and Policy, The Next Fifty Years. Bloomington: Indiana University Press. Also see report in Engineering News-Record, 29. October 12
  - "Influencing the Future of New York City." Urban Action and Experimentation Program, Institute of Urban Environment, 1967-10-17 (Box 120)
  - On Harvard's Planning Division, 1968-06-18 (Box 120)
    Memorandum
  - To the National Commission on Urban Problems, 1968-07-11 (Box 120)
  - "Noise and Planning." Federal Panel on Noise Abatement, 1968-10-31 (Box 120)
  - "Aesthetics and Human Values." New England Regional Conference, AIA, 1968-11-07 (Box 120)
    >New Haven
  - "Invasion and Counterattack." Violence in America: A Historical and Contemporary Reader, edited by Thomas Rose, 1970 (Box 120)
    Vintage Books/ Random House. Chapter 14,18
  - Africa, Undated (Box 121)
  - Comments on a paper by Mr. Millikan, Undated (Box 121)
  - History of Housing, Undated (Box 121)
  - "Kingsview Homes, Inc.", Undated (Box 121)
  - "On the Desirability of an Anti-Bias Ordinance in San Francisco's Urban Redevelopment Program." For the Council for Civic Unity., Undated (Box 121)
  - Invitations Refused, Undated (Box 121)
  - New York Post drafts, 1948-1949 (Box 121)
- Series VI. Book Manuscripts
  - The City is the Frontier (Box 65)
    Also available on Reel 36
  - The City is the Frontier-Forbidden Neighbors (Box 66)
    Also available on Reels 36 and 37
  - Future of Housing-Housing Program for America (Box 67)
    Also available on Reel 37
  - Man's Struggle for Shelter (Box 68)
    Also available on Reels 37 and 38
  - Revolution in Land-Squatter Settlement (Box 69)
    Also available on Reel 38
  - Critiques by Crosby and Rodwin, Undated (Box 121)
  - The City is the Frontier, Undated (Box 121)
  - Forbidden Neighbors, Undated (Box 121)
  - Future of Housing including a copy marked for revision, Undated (Box 121)
  - Language of Cities, Undated (Box 121)
  - Man's Struggle for Shelter, Undated (Box 121)
  - Squatter Settlements: The Problem and the Opportunity. Ideas and Methods Exchange No. 63; 302 Urban Planning. Agency for International Affairs, Division of International Affairs, Department of Housing and Urban Development, 1966-04 (Box 121)
    >Washington, D. C.
- Series VII. Topics
  - Alaska-Bibliographies (Box 70)
    Also available on Reel 39
  - Bolivia-Calcutta (Box 71)
    Also available on Reel 40
  - California (Box 72)
    Also available on Reels 40 and 41
  - California - Clippings and News Releases, (undated) (Box 73)
    Also available on Reel 41
  - Canada-Chicago, 1948-1951 (Box 74)
    Also available on Reel 42
  - Chicago (undated)-Chile, 1966-1968 (Box 75)
  - Cicero-Colombia (Box 76)
    Also available on Reel 43
  - Connecticut Housing-Current History (Box 77)
  - Defense Housing-Discrimination (Box 78)
    Also available on Reel 44
  - Discrimination (Box 79)
  - Discrimination-Elderly (Box 80)
    Also available on Reels 44 and 45
  - Federal Housing (Box 81)
    Also available on Reel 45
  - Ghana (Box 82)
    Also available on Reel 46
  - Harlem-Frank Horne (Box 83)
  - Housing (Box 84)
  - Ireland-Japan (Box 85)
    Also available on Reel 47
  - Kenya-Negro Mortgage Company (Box 86)
    Also available on Reel 48
  - Negro Housing-New York City Municipal Law (Box 87)
  - New York State Legislature-Pakistan (Box 88)
    Also available on Reel 49
  - Philadelphia-Refugee Planners (Box 89)
    Also available on Reels 49 and 50
  - Restrictive Covenants-Singapore (Box 90)
    Also available on Reel 50
  - Stuyvesant Town (Box 91)
  - Turkey-World Trade Center (Box 92)
    Also available on Reel 51
  - Papers by Catherine Bauer, 1939-1959 (Box 121)
  - Prefabricated Lustron Housing, 1949 (Box 121)
  - Slum Clearance, 1948 (Box 121)
  - Urban Renewal papers by Morton J. Schussheim, Undated (Box 121)
- Series VIII. Scrapbook
  - 1938-1946 (Box 93)
    Also available on Reel 52
  - 1947-1954 (Box 94)
  - 1955 (Box 95)
  - 1955-1958 (Box 96)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 97)
    Also available on Reel 53
  - undated (Box 98)
  - Scrapbook, 1955 (Box 122)
  - Eight Recorded Speeches, Undated (Box 122)
  - "Yes, We Can Have Housing," filmstrip produced by U. S. Housing Authority, Federal Works Agency, Washington, D. C., 1944 (Box 122)
- Series IX. Personal
  - Correspondence (Box 99)
    Also available on Reels 53 and 54
  - Finances (Box 100)
    Also available on Reel 54
- Series for box 101-122 (Box 101-122)
  A supplemental guide, covering boxes 101 to 122, is available by clicking here. 100 KB PDF
- Continuation of Box List
  - Advisory Council on Human Settlements (Box 123, Folder 1)
  - Action, Inc. (Box 123, Folder 2)
  - Action, Inc. (1) (Box 123, Folder 3)
  - Action, Inc. (2) (Box 123, Folder 4)
  - Action, Inc (3) (Box 123, Folder 5)
  - Action, Inc (4) (Box 123, Folder 6)
  - Action, Inc. (Box 123, Folder 7)
  - American Institute of Planners, 1961 (Box 124, Folder 1)
  - American Institute of Planners, 1962 (Box 124, Folder 2)
  - American Institute of Planners, 1963-1964 (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - American Institute of Planners, 1960 (Box 124, Folder 4)
  - American Institute of Planners, 1967 (Box 124, Folder 5)
  - American Institute of Planners, 1968 (Box 124, Folder 6)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1945-1946 (Box 125, Folder 1)
  - Americans for Democratic Action (1), 1947 (Box 125, Folder 2)
  - Americans for Democratic Action (2), 1947 (Box 125, Folder 3)
  - Americans for Democratic Action (3), 1947 (Box 125, Folder 4)
  - Americans for Democratic Action (4), 1947 (Box 125, Folder 5)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1945-1947> (Box 125, Folder 6)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1948-1950 (Box 125, Folder 7)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1951-1955 (Box 125, Folder 8)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1952-1956 (Box 125, Folder 9)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1962 (Box 125, Folder 10)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1963 (Box 125, Folder 11)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1964-1966 (Box 125, Folder 12)
  - Agency for International Development, 1963 (Box 126, Folder 1)
  - Agency for International Development (1), 1964 (Box 126, Folder 2)
  - Agency for International Development (2), April-May 1964 (Box 126, Folder 3)
  - Agency for International Development(3), June-December 1964 (Box 126, Folder 4)
  - Agency for International Development 1965, 1965 (Box 126, Folder 5)
  - Agency for International Development, 1966 (Box 126, Folder 6)
  - Agency for International Development - Advisory Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 126, Folder 7)
  - Agency for International Development - Advisory Committee, 1968 (Box 126, Folder 8)
  - American Jewish Committee, 1950-1952 (Box 127, Folder 1)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1948-1958 (Box 127, Folder 2)
  - American Jewish Committee 1955-1958 (Box 127, Folder 3)
  - American Jewish Congress (1), 1958 (Box 127, Folder 4)
  - American Jewish Congress (2), 1959 (Box 127, Folder 5)
  - American Jewish Congress (3), 1959 (Box 127, Folder 6)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1960-161 (Box 127, Folder 7)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1961 (Box 127, Folder 8)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1961-1962 (Box 127, Folder 9)
  - American Jewish Congress (1), 1963 (Box 128, Folder 1)
  - American Jewish Congress (2), 1963 (Box 128, Folder 2)
  - American Jewish Congress (3), 1963 (Box 128, Folder 3)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1964-1966 (Box 128, Folder 4)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1965-1966 (Box 128, Folder 5)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1967-1968 (Box 128, Folder 6)
  - American Society of Consulting Planners, 1968 (Box 129, Folder 1)
  - American Society of Planners and Architects, 1946-1947 (Box 129, Folder 2)
  - American Society of Planning Officials, 1947-1952 (Box 129, Folder 3)
  - American Society of Planning Officials, 1953 (Box 129, Folder 4)
  - American Society of Planning Officials, 1954 (Box 129, Folder 5)
  - American Society of Planning Officials, 1955 (Box 129, Folder 6)
  - American Society of Planning Officials (1), 1958-1960 (Box 129, Folder 7)
  - American Society of Planning Officials 1961 (Box 129, Folder 8)
  - Amdrican Society of Planning Officials 1962 (Box 129, Folder 9)
  - American Society of Planning Officials 1965-1967 (Box 129, Folder 10)
  - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai Brith 1955-1962 (Box 130, Folder 1)
  - Architects' Renewal Committee in Harlem, Inc. 1966-1967 (Box 130, Folder 2)
  - Association of Collegiate Schools of Planning 1967-1968 (Box 130, Folder 3)
  - Boston Urban Renewal Program (Box 130, Folder 4)
  - Boston Urban Renewal Program - 1953 (Box 130, Folder 5)
  - Boston Urban Renewal Program 1968-1969 (Box 130, Folder 6)
  - Boston Urban Renewal Program 1969 (Box 130, Folder 7)
  - Bureau of Labor Statistics 1951-1954 (Box 130, Folder 8)
  - Columbia University Administration / Kirk and Truman (Box 131, Folder 1)
  - Columbia University Congratulatory Letter 1961-1965 (Box 131, Folder 2)
  - Columbia University Division of Urban Planning 1965-1968 (Box 131, Folder 3)
  - Columbia University - Division of Urban Planning (School of Architecture) 1962-1968 (1) (Box 131, Folder 4)
  - Columbia University - Division of Urban Planning (School of Architecture) 1969 (2) (Box 131, Folder 5)
  - Columbia University Term Classwork 1965-1966 (Box 131, Folder 6)
  - Columbia University, Institute of Urban Environment 1966-1968 (Box 132, Folder 1)
  - Columbia University - Introductory Course - Division of Urban Planning 1967-68 (Fall Term) (1) (Box 132, Folder 2)
  - Columbia University - Introductory Course - Division of Urban Planning 1967-68 (Fall Term) (2) (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Columbia University Personal Notebook 1968-1969 (Box 132, Folder 4)
  - Columbia university Problems in the Urbanizing World 1964-66 (1) (Box 133, Folder 1)
  - Columbia University - Problems in the Urbanizing World 1967 - (2) (Box 133, Folder 2)
  - Columbia University Reading Lists 1967-69 (1) (Box 133, Folder 3)
  - Columbia University - Reading Lists 1967-69 (2) (Box 133, Folder 4)
  - Columbia University - Urban Action and Experimental Program - 1966-1967 (Box 133, Folder 5)
  - Columbia University - Urban Action and Experimental Program 1968 (Box 133, Folder 6)